<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<root translation="NRSV">
  <book name="Genesis">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the beginning when God created the heavens and the earth,</verse>
      <verse name="2">the earth was a formless void and darkness covered the face of the deep, while a wind from God swept over the face of the waters.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Then God said, "Let there be light"; and there was light.</verse>
      <verse name="4">And God saw that the light was good; and God separated the light from the darkness.</verse>
      <verse name="5">God called the light Day, and the darkness he called Night. And there was evening and there was morning, the first day.</verse>
      <verse name="6">And God said, "Let there be a dome in the midst of the waters, and let it separate the waters from the waters."</verse>
      <verse name="7">So God made the dome and separated the waters that were under the dome from the waters that were above the dome. And it was so.</verse>
      <verse name="8">God called the dome Sky. And there was evening and there was morning, the second day.</verse>
      <verse name="9">And God said, "Let the waters under the sky be gathered together into one place, and let the dry land appear." And it was so.</verse>
      <verse name="10">God called the dry land Earth, and the waters that were gathered together he called Seas. And God saw that it was good.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Exodus">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">These are the names of the sons of Israel who came to Egypt with Jacob, each with his household:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah,</verse>
      <verse name="3">Issachar, Zebulun, and Benjamin,</verse>
      <verse name="4">Dan and Naphtali, Gad and Asher.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The total number of people born to Jacob was seventy. Joseph was already in Egypt.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Then Joseph died, and all his brothers, and that whole generation.</verse>
      <verse name="7">But the Israelites were fruitful and prolific; they multiplied and grew exceedingly strong, so that the land was filled with them.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Leviticus">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The Lord summoned Moses and spoke to him from the tent of meeting, saying:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Speak to the people of Israel and say to them: When any of you bring an offering of livestock to the Lord, you shall bring your offering from the herd or from the flock.</verse>
      <verse name="3">If the offering is a burnt offering from the herd, you shall offer a male without blemish; you shall bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting, for acceptance in your behalf before the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="4">You shall lay your hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it shall be acceptable in your behalf as atonement for you.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The bull shall be slaughtered before the Lord; and Aaron's sons the priests shall offer the blood, dashing the blood against all sides of the altar that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Numbers">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The Lord spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the tent of meeting, on the first day of the second month, in the second year after they had come out of the land of Egypt, saying:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Take a census of the whole congregation of Israelites, in their clans, by ancestral houses, according to the number of names, every male individually;</verse>
      <verse name="3">from twenty years old and upward, everyone in Israel able to go to war. You and Aaron shall enroll them, company by company.</verse>
      <verse name="4">A man from each tribe shall be with you, each man the head of his ancestral house.</verse>
      <verse name="5">These are the names of the men who shall assist you: From Reuben, Elizur son of Shedeur.</verse>
      <verse name="6">From Simeon, Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai.</verse>
      <verse name="7">From Judah, Nahshon son of Amminadab.</verse>
      <verse name="8">From Issachar, Nethanel son of Zuar.</verse>
      <verse name="9">From Zebulun, Eliab son of Helon.</verse>
      <verse name="10">From the sons of Joseph: from Ephraim, Elishama son of Ammihud; from Manasseh, Gamaliel son of Pedahzur.</verse>
      <verse name="11">From Benjamin, Abidan son of Gideoni.</verse>
      <verse name="12">From Dan, Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai.</verse>
      <verse name="13">From Asher, Pagiel son of Ochran.</verse>
      <verse name="14">From Gad, Eliasaph son of Deuel.</verse>
      <verse name="15">From Naphtali, Ahira son of Enan.</verse>
      <verse name="16">These were the ones chosen from the congregation, the leaders of their ancestral tribes, the heads of the divisions of Israel.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Deuteronomy">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">These are the words that Moses spoke to all Israel beyond the Jordan- in the wilderness, on the plain opposite Suph, between Paran and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Di-zahab.</verse>
      <verse name="2">(By the way of Mount Seir it takes eleven days to reach Kadesh-barnea from Horeb.)</verse>
      <verse name="3">In the fortieth year, on the first day of the eleventh month, Moses spoke to the Israelites just as the Lord had commanded him to speak to them.</verse>
      <verse name="4">This was after he had defeated King Sihon of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, and King Og of Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Beyond the Jordan in the land of Moab, Moses undertook to expound this law as follows:</verse>
      <verse name="6">The Lord our God spoke to us at Horeb, saying, "You have stayed long enough at this mountain.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Resume your journey, and go into the hill country of the Amorites as well as into the neighboring regions- the Arabah, the hill country, the Shephelah, the Negeb, and the seacoast -the land of the Canaanites and the Lebanon, as far as the great river, the river Euphrates.</verse>
      <verse name="8">See, I have set the land before you; go in and take possession of the land that I swore to your ancestors, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them and to their descendants after them."</verse>
      <verse name="9">At that time I said to you, "I am unable by myself to bear you.</verse>
      <verse name="10">The Lord your God has multiplied you, so that today you are as numerous as the stars of heaven.</verse>
      <verse name="11">May the Lord, the God of your ancestors, increase you a thousand times more and bless you, as he has promised you!</verse>
      <verse name="12">But how can I bear the heavy burden of your disputes all by myself?</verse>
      <verse name="13">Choose for each of your tribes individuals who are wise, discerning, and reputable to be your leaders."</verse>
      <verse name="14">You answered me, "The plan you have proposed is a good one."</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Joshua">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">After the death of Moses the servant of the Lord, the Lord spoke to Joshua son of Nun, Moses' assistant, saying,</verse>
      <verse name="2">"My servant Moses is dead. Now proceed to cross the Jordan, you and all this people, into the land that I am giving to them, to the Israelites.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Every place that the sole of your foot will tread upon I have given to you, as I promised to Moses.</verse>
      <verse name="4">From the wilderness and the Lebanon as far as the great river, the river Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites, to the Great Sea in the west shall be your territory.</verse>
      <verse name="5">No one shall be able to stand against you all the days of your life. As I was with Moses, so I will be with you; I will not fail you or forsake you.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Be strong and courageous; for you shall put this people in possession of the land that I swore to their ancestors to give them.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Judges">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">After the death of Joshua, the Israelites inquired of the Lord, "Who shall go up first for us against the Canaanites, to fight against them?"</verse>
      <verse name="2">The Lord said, "Judah shall go up. I hereby give the land into his hand."</verse>
      <verse name="3">Judah said to his brother Simeon, "Come up with me into the territory allotted to me, that we may fight against the Canaanites; then I too will go with you into the territory allotted to you." So Simeon went with him.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Then Judah went up and the Lord gave the Canaanites and the Perizzites into their hand; and they defeated ten thousand of them at Bezek.</verse>
      <verse name="5">They came upon Adoni-bezek at Bezek, and fought against him, and defeated the Canaanites and the Perizzites.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Adoni-bezek fled; but they pursued him, and caught him, and cut off his thumbs and big toes.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Adoni-bezek said, "Seventy kings with their thumbs and big toes cut off used to pick up scraps under my table; as I have done, so God has paid me back." They brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Then the people of Judah fought against Jerusalem and took it. They put it to the sword and set the city on fire.</verse>
      <verse name="9">Afterward the people of Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites who lived in the hill country, in the Negeb, and in the lowland.</verse>
      <verse name="10">Judah went against the Canaanites who lived in Hebron (the name of Hebron was formerly Kiriath-arba); and they defeated Sheshai and Ahiman and Talmai.</verse>
      <verse name="11">From there they went against the inhabitants of Debir (the name of Debir was formerly Kiriath-sepher).</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Ruth">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the days when the judges ruled, there was a famine in the land, and a certain man of Bethlehem in Judah went to live in the country of Moab, he and his wife and two sons.</verse>
      <verse name="2">The name of the man was Elimelech and the name of his wife Naomi, and the names of his two sons were Mahlon and Chilion; they were Ephrathites from Bethlehem in Judah. They went into the country of Moab and remained there.</verse>
      <verse name="3">But Elimelech, the husband of Naomi, died, and she was left with her two sons.</verse>
      <verse name="4">These took Moabite wives; the name of the one was Orpah and the name of the other Ruth. When they had lived there about ten years,</verse>
      <verse name="5">both Mahlon and Chilion also died, so that the woman was left without her two sons and her husband.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Then she started to return with her daughters-in-law from the country of Moab, for she had heard in the country of Moab that the Lord had considered his people and given them food.</verse>
      <verse name="7">So she set out from the place where she had been living, she and her two daughters-in-law, and they went on their way to go back to the land of Judah.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Samuel">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">There was a certain man of Ramathaim, a Zuphite from the hill country of Ephraim, whose name was Elkanah son of Jeroham son of Elihu son of Tohu son of Zuph, an Ephraimite.</verse>
      <verse name="2">He had two wives; the name of the one was Hannah, and the name of the other Peninnah. Peninnah had children, but Hannah had no children.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Now this man used to go up year by year from his town to worship and to sacrifice to the Lord of hosts at Shiloh, where the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were priests of the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="4">On the day when Elkanah sacrificed, he would give portions to his wife Peninnah and to all her sons and daughters;</verse>
      <verse name="5">but to Hannah he gave a double portion, because he loved her, though the Lord had closed her womb.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Her rival used to provoke her severely, to irritate her, because the Lord had closed her womb.</verse>
      <verse name="7">So it went on year by year; as often as she went up to the house of the Lord, she used to provoke her. Therefore Hannah wept and would not eat.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Her husband Elkanah said to her, "Hannah, why do you weep? Why do you not eat? Why is your heart sad? Am I not more to you than ten sons?"</verse>
      <verse name="9">After they had eaten and drunk at Shiloh, Hannah rose and presented herself before the Lord. Now Eli the priest was sitting on the seat beside the doorpost of the temple of the Lord.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Samuel">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">After the death of Saul, when David had returned from defeating the Amalekites, David remained two days in Ziklag.</verse>
      <verse name="2">On the third day, a man came from Saul's camp, with his clothes torn and dirt on his head. When he came to David, he fell to the ground and did obeisance.</verse>
      <verse name="3">David said to him, "Where have you come from?" He said to him, "I have escaped from the camp of Israel."</verse>
      <verse name="4">David said to him, "How did things go? Tell me!" He answered, "The army fled from the battle, but also many of the army fell and died; and Saul and his son Jonathan also died."</verse>
      <verse name="5">Then David asked the young man who was reporting to him, "How do you know that Saul and his son Jonathan died?"</verse>
      <verse name="6">The young man reporting to him said, "I happened to be on Mount Gilboa; and there was Saul leaning on his spear, while the chariots and the horsemen drew close to him.</verse>
      <verse name="7">When he looked behind him, he saw me, and called to me. I answered, 'Here sir.'</verse>
      <verse name="8">And he said to me, 'Who are you?' I answered him, 'I am an Amalekite.'</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Kings">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">King David was old and advanced in years; and although they covered him with clothes, he could not get warm.</verse>
      <verse name="2">So his servants said to him, "Let a young virgin be sought for my lord the king, and let her wait on the king, and be his attendant; let her lie in your bosom, so that my lord the king may be warm."</verse>
      <verse name="3">So they searched for a beautiful girl throughout all the territory of Israel, and found Abishag the Shunammite, and brought her to the king.</verse>
      <verse name="4">The girl was very beautiful. She became the king's attendant and served him, but the king did not know her sexually.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Now Adonijah son of Haggith exalted himself, saying, "I will be king"; he prepared for himself chariots and horsemen, and fifty men to run before him.</verse>
      <verse name="6">His father had never at any time displeased him by asking, "Why have you done thus and so?" He was also a very handsome man, and he was born next after Absalom.</verse>
      <verse name="7">He conferred with Joab son of Zeruiah and with the priest Abiathar, and they supported Adonijah.</verse>
      <verse name="8">But the priest Zadok, and Benaiah son of Jehoiada, and the prophet Nathan, and Shimei, and Rei, and David's own warriors did not side with Adonijah.</verse>
      <verse name="9">Adonijah sacrificed sheep, oxen, and fatted cattle by the stone Zoheleth, which is beside En-rogel, and he invited all his brothers, the king's sons, and all the royal officials of Judah,</verse>
      <verse name="10">but he did not invite the prophet Nathan or Benaiah or the warriors or his brother Solomon.</verse>
      <verse name="11">Then Nathan said to Bathsheba, Solomon's mother, "Have you not heard that Adonijah son of Haggith has become king and our lord David does not know it?</verse>
      <verse name="12">Now therefore come, let me give you advice, so that you may save your own life and the life of your son Solomon.</verse>
      <verse name="13">Go in at once to King David, and say to him, 'Did you not, my lord the king, swear to your servant, saying: Your son Solomon shall succeed me as king, and he shall sit on my throne? Why then is Adonijah king?'</verse>
      <verse name="14">Then while you are still there speaking with the king, I will come in after you and confirm your words."</verse>
      <verse name="15">So Bathsheba went to the king in his room. The king was very old; Abishag the Shunammite was attending the king.</verse>
      <verse name="16">Bathsheba bowed and did obeisance to the king, and the king said, "What do you wish?"</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Kings">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">After the death of Ahab, Moab rebelled against Israel.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Ahaziah had fallen through the lattice in his upper chamber in Samaria, and lay injured; so he sent messengers, telling them, "Go, inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron, whether I shall recover from this injury."</verse>
      <verse name="3">But the angel of the Lord said to Elijah the Tishbite, "Get up, go to meet the messengers of the king of Samaria, and say to them, 'Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are going to inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron?'</verse>
      <verse name="4">Now therefore thus says the Lord, 'You shall not leave the bed to which you have gone, but you shall surely die.'" So Elijah went.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The messengers returned to the king, who said to them, "Why have you returned?"</verse>
      <verse name="6">They answered him, "There came a man to meet us, who said to us, 'Go back to the king who sent you, and say to him: Thus says the Lord: Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are sending to inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron? Therefore you shall not leave the bed to which you have gone, but shall surely die.'"</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Chronicles">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Adam, Seth, Enosh;</verse>
      <verse name="2">Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared;</verse>
      <verse name="3">Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech;</verse>
      <verse name="4">Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The descendants of Japheth: Gomer, Magog, Madai, Javan, Tubal, Meshech, and Tiras.</verse>
      <verse name="6">The descendants of Gomer: Ashkenaz, Diphath, and Togarmah.</verse>
      <verse name="7">The descendants of Javan: Elishah, Tarshish, Kittim, and Rodanim.</verse>
      <verse name="8">The descendants of Ham: Cush, Egypt, Put, and Canaan.</verse>
      <verse name="9">The descendants of Cush: Seba, Havilah, Sabta, Raama, and Sabteca. The descendants of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.</verse>
      <verse name="10">Cush became the father of Nimrod; he was the first to be a mighty one on the earth.</verse>
      <verse name="11">Egypt became the father of Ludim, Anamim, Lehabim, Naphtuhim,</verse>
      <verse name="12">Pathrusim, Casluhim, and Caphtorim, from whom the Philistines come.</verse>
      <verse name="13">Canaan became the father of Sidon his firstborn, and Heth,</verse>
      <verse name="14">and the Jebusites, the Amorites, the Girgashites,</verse>
      <verse name="15">the Hivites, the Arkites, the Sinites,</verse>
      <verse name="16">the Arvadites, the Zemarites, and the Hamathites.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Chronicles">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Solomon son of David established himself in his kingdom; the Lord his God was with him and made him exceedingly great.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Solomon summoned all Israel, the commanders of the thousands and of the hundreds, the judges, and all the leaders of all Israel, the heads of families.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Then Solomon, and the whole assembly with him, went to the high place that was at Gibeon; for God's tent of meeting, which Moses the servant of the Lord had made in the wilderness, was there.</verse>
      <verse name="4">(But David had brought the ark of God up from Kiriath-jearim to the place that David had prepared for it; for he had pitched a tent for it in Jerusalem.)</verse>
      <verse name="5">Moreover the bronze altar that Bezalel son of Uri, son of Hur, had made, was there in front of the tabernacle of the Lord. And Solomon and the assembly inquired at it.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Ezra">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the first year of King Cyrus of Persia, in order that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, the Lord stirred up the spirit of King Cyrus of Persia so that he sent a herald throughout all his kingdom, and also in a</verse>
      <verse name="2"> written edict declared:</verse>
      <verse name="3">Any of those among you who are of his people- may their God be with them! -are now permitted to go up to Jerusalem in Judah, and rebuild the house of the Lord, the God of Israel- he is the God who is in Jerusalem;</verse>
      <verse name="4">and let all survivors, in whatever place they reside, be assisted by the people of their place with silver and gold, with goods and with animals, besides freewill offerings for the house of God in Jerusalem."</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Nehemiah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The words of Nehemiah son of Hacaliah. In the month of Chislev, in the twentieth year, while I was in Susa the capital,</verse>
      <verse name="2">one of my brothers, Hanani, came with certain men from Judah; and I asked them about the Jews that survived, those who had escaped the captivity, and about Jerusalem.</verse>
      <verse name="3">They replied, "The survivors there in the province who escaped captivity are in great trouble and shame; the wall of Jerusalem is broken down, and its gates have been destroyed by fire."</verse>
      <verse name="4">When I heard these words I sat down and wept, and mourned for days, fasting and praying before the God of heaven.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Esther">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">This happened in the days of Ahasuerus, the same Ahasuerus who ruled over one hundred twenty-seven provinces from India to Ethiopia.</verse>
      <verse name="2">In those days when King Ahasuerus sat on his royal throne in the citadel of Susa,</verse>
      <verse name="3">in the third year of his reign, he gave a banquet for all his officials and ministers. The army of Persia and Media and the nobles and governors of the provinces were present,</verse>
      <verse name="4">while he displayed the great wealth of his kingdom and the splendor and pomp of his majesty for many days, one hundred eighty days in all.</verse>
      <verse name="5">When these days were completed, the king gave for all the people present in the citadel of Susa, both great and small, a banquet lasting for seven days, in the court of the garden of the king's palace.</verse>
      <verse name="6">There were white cotton curtains and blue hangings tied with cords of fine linen and purple to silver rings and marble pillars. There were couches of gold and silver on a mosaic pavement of porphyry, marble, mother-of-pearl, and colored stones.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Drinks were served in golden goblets, goblets of different kinds, and the royal wine was lavished according to the bounty of the king.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Job">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">There was once a man in the land of Uz whose name was Job. That man was blameless and upright, one who feared God and turned away from evil.</verse>
      <verse name="2">There were born to him seven sons and three daughters.</verse>
      <verse name="3">He had seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred donkeys, and very many servants; so that this man was the greatest of all the people of the east.</verse>
      <verse name="4">His sons used to go and hold feasts in one another's houses in turn; and they would send and invite their three sisters to eat and drink with them.</verse>
      <verse name="5">And when the feast days had run their course, Job would send and sanctify them, and he would rise early in the morning and offer burnt offerings according to the number of them all; for Job said, "It may be that my children have sinned, and cursed God in their hearts." This is what Job always did.</verse>
      <verse name="6">One day the heavenly beings came to present themselves before the Lord, and Satan also came among them.</verse>
      <verse name="7">The Lord said to Satan, "Where have you come from?" Satan answered the Lord, "From going to and fro on the earth, and from walking up and down on it."</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Psalms">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Happy are those who do not follow the advice of the wicked, or take the path that sinners tread, or sit in the seat of scoffers;</verse>
      <verse name="2">but their delight is in the law of the Lord, and on his law they meditate day and night.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Proverbs">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The proverbs of Solomon son of David, king of Israel:</verse>
      <verse name="2">For learning about wisdom and instruction, for understanding words of insight,</verse>
      <verse name="3">for gaining instruction in wise dealing, righteousness, justice, and equity;</verse>
      <verse name="4">to teach shrewdness to the simple, knowledge and prudence to the young-</verse>
      <verse name="5">let the wise also hear and gain in learning, and the discerning acquire skill,</verse>
      <verse name="6">to understand a proverb and a figure, the words of the wise and their riddles.</verse>
      <verse name="7">The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge; fools despise wisdom and instruction.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Hear, my child, your father's instruction, and do not reject your mother's teaching;</verse>
      <verse name="9">for they are a fair garland for your head, and pendants for your neck.</verse>
      <verse name="10">My child, if sinners entice you, do not consent.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Ecclesiastes">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The words of the Teacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Vanity of vanities, says the Teacher, vanity of vanities! All is vanity.</verse>
      <verse name="3">What do people gain from all the toil at which they toil under the sun?</verse>
      <verse name="4">A generation goes, and a generation comes, but the earth remains forever.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The sun rises and the sun goes down, and hurries to the place where it rises.</verse>
      <verse name="6">The wind blows to the south, and goes around to the north; round and round goes the wind, and on its circuits the wind returns.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Song of Songs">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The Song of Songs, which is Solomon's.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth! For your love is better than wine,</verse>
      <verse name="3">your anointing oils are fragrant, your name is perfume poured out; therefore the maidens love you.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Draw me after you, let us make haste. The king has brought me into his chambers. We will exult and rejoice in you; we will extol your love more than wine; rightly do they love you.</verse>
      <verse name="5">I am black and beautiful, O daughters of Jerusalem, like the tents of Kedar, like the curtains of Solomon.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Isaiah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The vision of Isaiah son of Amoz, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Hear, O heavens, and listen, O earth; for the Lord has spoken: I reared children and brought them up, but they have rebelled against me.</verse>
      <verse name="3">The ox knows its owner, and the donkey its master's crib; but Israel does not know, my people do not understand.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Ah, sinful nation, people laden with iniquity, offspring who do evil, children who deal corruptly, who have forsaken the Lord, who have despised the Holy One of Israel, who are utterly estranged!</verse>
      <verse name="5">Why do you seek further beatings? Why do you continue to rebel? The whole head is sick, and the whole heart faint.</verse>
      <verse name="6">From the sole of the foot even to the head, there is no soundness in it, but bruises and sores and bleeding wounds; they have not been drained, or bound up, or softened with oil.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Your country lies desolate, your cities are burned with fire; in your very presence aliens devour your land; it is desolate, as overthrown by foreigners.</verse>
      <verse name="8">And daughter Zion is left like a booth in a vineyard, like a shelter in a cucumber field, like a besieged city.</verse>
      <verse name="9">If the Lord of hosts had not left us a few survivors, we would have been like Sodom, and become like Gomorrah.</verse>
      <verse name="10">Hear the word of the Lord, you rulers of Sodom! Listen to the teaching of our God, you people of Gomorrah!</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Jeremiah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The words of Jeremiah son of Hilkiah, of the priests who were in Anathoth in the land of Benjamin,</verse>
      <verse name="2">to whom the word of the Lord came in the days of King Josiah son of Amon of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign.</verse>
      <verse name="3">It came also in the days of King Jehoiakim son of Josiah of Judah, and until the end of the eleventh year of King Zedekiah son of Josiah of Judah, until the captivity of Jerusalem in the fifth month.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Now the word of the Lord came to me saying,</verse>
      <verse name="5">"Before I formed you in the womb I knew you, and before you were born I consecrated you; I appointed you a prophet to the nations."</verse>
      <verse name="6">Then I said, "Ah, Lord God! Truly I do not know how to speak, for I am only a boy."</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Lamentations of Jeremiah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">How lonely sits the city that once was full of people! How like a widow she has become, she that was great among the nations! She that was a princess among the provinces has become a vassal.</verse>
      <verse name="2">She weeps bitterly in the night, with tears on her cheeks; among all her lovers she has no one to comfort her; all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, they have become her enemies.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Judah has gone into exile with suffering and hard servitude; she lives now among the nations, and finds no resting place; her pursuers have all overtaken her in the midst of her distress.</verse>
      <verse name="4">The roads to Zion mourn, for no one comes to the festivals; all her gates are desolate, her priests groan; her young girls grieve, and her lot is bitter.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Her foes have become the masters, her enemies prosper, because the Lord has made her suffer for the multitude of her transgressions; her children have gone away, captives before the foe.</verse>
      <verse name="6">From daughter Zion has departed all her majesty. Her princes have become like stags that find no pasture; they fled without strength before the pursuer.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Jerusalem remembers, in the days of her affliction and wandering, all the precious things that were hers in days of old. When her people fell into the hand of the foe, and there was no one to help her, the foe looked on mocking over her downfall.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Ezekiel">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the thirtieth year, in the fourth month, on the fifth day of the month, as I was among the exiles by the river Chebar, the heavens were opened, and I saw visions of God.</verse>
      <verse name="2">On the fifth day of the month (it was the fifth year of the exile of King Jehoiachin),</verse>
      <verse name="3">the word of the Lord came to the priest Ezekiel son of Buzi, in the land of the Chaldeans by the river Chebar; and the hand of the Lord was on him there.</verse>
      <verse name="4">As I looked, a stormy wind came out of the north: a great cloud with brightness around it and fire flashing forth continually, and in the middle of the fire, something like gleaming amber.</verse>
      <verse name="5">In the middle of it was something like four living creatures. This was their appearance: they were of human form.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Each had four faces, and each of them had four wings.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Their legs were straight, and the soles of their feet were like the sole of a calf's foot; and they sparkled like burnished bronze.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Under their wings on their four sides they had human hands. And the four had their faces and their wings thus:</verse>
      <verse name="9">their wings touched one another; each of them moved straight ahead, without turning as they moved.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Daniel">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the third year of the reign of King Jehoiakim of Judah, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon came to Jerusalem and besieged it.</verse>
      <verse name="2">The Lord let King Jehoiakim of Judah fall into his power, as well as some of the vessels of the house of God. These he brought to the land of Shinar, and placed the vessels in the treasury of his gods.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Then the king commanded his palace master Ashpenaz to bring some of the Israelites of the royal family and of the nobility,</verse>
      <verse name="4">young men without physical defect and handsome, versed in every branch of wisdom, endowed with knowledge and insight, and competent to serve in the king's palace; they were to be taught the literature and language of the Chaldeans.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The king assigned them a daily portion of the royal rations of food and wine. They were to be educated for three years, so that at the end of that time they could be stationed in the king's court.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Among them were Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, from the tribe of Judah.</verse>
      <verse name="7">The palace master gave them other names: Daniel he called Belteshazzar, Hananiah he called Shadrach, Mishael he called Meshach, and Azariah he called Abednego.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Hosea">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The word of the Lord that came to Hosea son of Beeri, in the days of Kings Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah of Judah, and in the days of King Jeroboam son of Joash of Israel.</verse>
      <verse name="2">When the Lord first spoke through Hosea, the Lord said to Hosea, "Go, take for yourself a wife of whoredom and have children of whoredom, for the land commits great whoredom by forsaking the Lord."</verse>
      <verse name="3">So he went and took Gomer daughter of Diblaim, and she conceived and bore him a son.</verse>
      <verse name="4">And the Lord said to him, "Name him Jezreel; for in a little while I will punish the house of Jehu for the blood of Jezreel, and I will put an end to the kingdom of the house of Israel.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Joel">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The word of the Lord that came to Joel son of Pethuel:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Hear this, O elders, give ear, all inhabitants of the land! Has such a thing happened in your days, or in the days of your ancestors?</verse>
      <verse name="3">Tell your children of it, and let your children tell their children, and their children another generation.</verse>
      <verse name="4">What the cutting locust left, the swarming locust has eaten. What the swarming locust left, the hopping locust has eaten, and what the hopping locust left, the destroying locust has eaten.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Wake up, you drunkards, and weep; and wail, all you wine-drinkers, over the sweet wine, for it is cut off from your mouth.</verse>
      <verse name="6">For a nation has invaded my land, powerful and innumerable; its teeth are lions' teeth, and it has the fangs of a lioness.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Amos">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The words of Amos, who was among the shepherds of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of King Uzziah of Judah and in the days of King Jeroboam son of Joash of Israel, two years before the earthquake.</verse>
      <verse name="2">And he said: The Lord roars from Zion, and utters his voice from Jerusalem; the pastures of the shepherds wither, and the top of Carmel dries up.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Thus says the Lord: For three transgressions of Damascus, and for four, I will not revoke the punishment; because they have threshed Gilead with threshing sledges of iron.</verse>
      <verse name="4">So I will send a fire on the house of Hazael, and it shall devour the strongholds of Ben-hadad.</verse>
      <verse name="5">I will break the gate bars of Damascus, and cut off the inhabitants from the Valley of Aven, and the one who holds the scepter from Beth-eden; and the people of Aram shall go into exile to Kir, says the Lord.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Obadiah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The vision of Obadiah. Thus says the Lord God concerning Edom: We have heard a report from the Lord, and a messenger has been sent among the nations: "Rise up! Let us rise against it for battle!"</verse>
      <verse name="2">I will surely make you least among the nations; you shall be utterly despised.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Your proud heart has deceived you, you that live in the clefts of the rock, whose dwelling is in the heights. You say in your heart, "Who will bring me down to the ground?"</verse>
      <verse name="4">Though you soar aloft like the eagle, though your nest is set among the stars, from there I will bring you down, says the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="5">If thieves came to you, if plunderers by night -how you have been destroyed!- would they not steal only what they wanted? If grape-gatherers came to you, would they not leave gleanings?</verse>
      <verse name="6">How Esau has been pillaged, his treasures searched out!</verse>
      <verse name="7">All your allies have deceived you, they have driven you to the border; your confederates have prevailed against you; those who ate your bread have set a trap for you- there is no understanding of it.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Jonah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Now the word of the Lord came to Jonah son of Amittai, saying,</verse>
      <verse name="2">"Go at once to Nineveh, that great city, and cry out against it; for their wickedness has come up before me."</verse>
      <verse name="3">But Jonah set out to flee to Tarshish from the presence of the Lord. He went down to Joppa and found a ship going to Tarshish; so he paid his fare and went on board, to go with them to Tarshish, away from the presence of the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="4">But the Lord hurled a great wind upon the sea, and such a mighty storm came upon the sea that the ship threatened to break up.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Then the mariners were afraid, and each cried to his god. They threw the cargo that was in the ship into the sea, to lighten it for them. Jonah, meanwhile, had gone down into the hold of the ship and had lain down, and was fast asleep.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Micah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The word of the Lord that came to Micah of Moresheth in the days of Kings Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Hear, you peoples, all of you; listen, O earth, and all that is in it; and let the Lord God be a witness against you, the Lord from his holy temple.</verse>
      <verse name="3">For lo, the Lord is coming out of his place, and will come down and tread upon the high places of the earth.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Then the mountains will melt under him and the valleys will burst open, like wax near the fire, like waters poured down a steep place.</verse>
      <verse name="5">All this is for the transgression of Jacob and for the sins of the house of Israel. What is the transgression of Jacob? Is it not Samaria? And what is the high place of Judah? Is it not Jerusalem?</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Nahum">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">An oracle concerning Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum of Elkosh.</verse>
      <verse name="2">A jealous and avenging God is the Lord, the Lord is avenging and wrathful; the Lord takes vengeance on his adversaries and rages against his enemies.</verse>
      <verse name="3">The Lord is slow to anger but great in power, and the Lord will by no means clear the guilty. His way is in whirlwind and storm, and the clouds are the dust of his feet.</verse>
      <verse name="4">He rebukes the sea and makes it dry, and he dries up all the rivers; Bashan and Carmel wither, and the bloom of Lebanon fades.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The mountains quake before him, and the hills melt; the earth heaves before him, the world and all who live in it.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Habakkuk">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The oracle that the prophet Habakkuk saw.</verse>
      <verse name="2">O Lord, how long shall I cry for help, and you will not listen? Or cry to you "Violence!" and you will not save?</verse>
      <verse name="3">Why do you make me see wrong-doing and look at trouble? Destruction and violence are before me; strife and contention arise.</verse>
      <verse name="4">So the law becomes slack and justice never prevails. The wicked surround the righteous- therefore judgment comes forth perverted.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Look at the nations, and see! Be astonished! Be astounded! For a work is being done in your days that you would not believe if you were told.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Zephaniah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The word of the Lord that came to Zephaniah son of Cushi son of Gedaliah son of Amariah son of Hezekiah, in the days of King Josiah son of Amon of Judah.</verse>
      <verse name="2">I will utterly sweep away everything from the face of the earth, says the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="3">I will sweep away humans and animals; I will sweep away the birds of the air and the fish of the sea. I will make the wicked stumble. I will cut off humanity from the face of the earth, says the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="4">I will stretch out my hand against Judah, and against all the inhabitants of Jerusalem; and I will cut off from this place every remnant of Baal and the name of the idolatrous priests;</verse>
      <verse name="5">those who bow down on the roofs to the host of the heavens; those who bow down and swear to the Lord, but also swear by Milcom;</verse>
      <verse name="6">those who have turned back from following the Lord, who have not sought the Lord or inquired of him.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Haggai">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the second year of King Darius, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of the Lord came by the prophet Haggai to Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua son of Jehozadak, the high priest:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Thus says the Lord of hosts: These people say the time has not yet come to rebuild the Lord's house.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Then the word of the Lord came by the prophet Haggai, saying:</verse>
      <verse name="4">Is it a time for you yourselves to live in your paneled houses, while this house lies in ruins?</verse>
      <verse name="5">Now therefore thus says the Lord of hosts: Consider how you have fared.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Zechariah">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, the word of the Lord came to the prophet Zechariah son of Berechiah son of Iddo, saying:</verse>
      <verse name="2">The Lord was very angry with your ancestors.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Therefore say to them, Thus says the Lord of hosts: Return to me, says the Lord of hosts, and I will return to you, says the Lord of hosts.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Do not be like your ancestors, to whom the former prophets proclaimed, "Thus says the Lord of hosts, Return from your evil ways and from your evil deeds." But they did not hear or heed me, says the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Your ancestors, where are they? And the prophets, do they live forever?</verse>
      <verse name="6">But my words and my statutes, which I commanded my servants the prophets, did they not overtake your ancestors? So they repented and said, "The Lord of hosts has dealt with us according to our ways and deeds, just as he planned to do."</verse>
      <verse name="7">On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, the month of Shebat, in the second year of Darius, the word of the Lord came to the prophet Zechariah son of Berechiah son of Iddo; and Zechariah said,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Malachi">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">An oracle. The word of the Lord to Israel by Malachi.</verse>
      <verse name="2">I have loved you, says the Lord. But you say, "How have you loved us?" Is not Esau Jacob's brother? says the Lord. Yet I have loved Jacob</verse>
      <verse name="3">but I have hated Esau; I have made his hill country a desolation and his heritage a desert for jackals.</verse>
      <verse name="4">If Edom says, "We are shattered but we will rebuild the ruins," the Lord of hosts says: They may build, but I will tear down, until they are called the wicked country, the people with whom the Lord is angry forever.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Your own eyes shall see this, and you shall say, "Great is the Lord beyond the borders of Israel!"</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Matthew">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">An account of the genealogy of Jesus the Messiah, the son of David, the son of Abraham.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Abraham was the father of Isaac, and Isaac the father of Jacob, and Jacob the father of Judah and his brothers,</verse>
      <verse name="3">and Judah the father of Perez and Zerah by Tamar, and Perez the father of Hezron, and Hezron the father of Aram,</verse>
      <verse name="4">and Aram the father of Aminadab, and Aminadab the father of Nahshon, and Nahshon the father of Salmon,</verse>
      <verse name="5">and Salmon the father of Boaz by Rahab, and Boaz the father of Obed by Ruth, and Obed the father of Jesse,</verse>
      <verse name="6">and Jesse the father of King David. And David was the father of Solomon by the wife of Uriah,</verse>
      <verse name="7">and Solomon the father of Rehoboam, and Rehoboam the father of Abijah, and Abijah the father of Asaph,</verse>
      <verse name="8">and Asaph the father of Jehoshaphat, and Jehoshaphat the father of Joram, and Joram the father of Uzziah,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Mark">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The beginning of the good news of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.</verse>
      <verse name="2">As it is written in the prophet Isaiah, "See, I am sending my messenger ahead of you, who will prepare your way;</verse>
      <verse name="3">the voice of one crying out in the wilderness: 'Prepare the way of the Lord, make his paths straight,'"</verse>
      <verse name="4">John the baptizer appeared in the wilderness, proclaiming a baptism of repentance for the forgiveness of sins.</verse>
      <verse name="5">And people from the whole Judean countryside and all the people of Jerusalem were going out to him, and were baptized by him in the river Jordan, confessing their sins.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Now John was clothed with camel's hair, with a leather belt around his waist, and he ate locusts and wild honey.</verse>
      <verse name="7">He proclaimed, "The one who is more powerful than I is coming after me; I am not worthy to stoop down and untie the thong of his sandals.</verse>
      <verse name="8">I have baptized you with water; but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit."</verse>
      <verse name="9">In those days Jesus came from Nazareth of Galilee and was baptized by John in the Jordan.</verse>
      <verse name="10">And just as he was coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens torn apart and the Spirit descending like a dove on him.</verse>
      <verse name="11">And a voice came from heaven, "You are my Son, the Beloved; with you I am well pleased."</verse>
      <verse name="12">And the Spirit immediately drove him out into the wilderness.</verse>
      <verse name="13">He was in the wilderness forty days, tempted by Satan; and he was with the wild beasts; and the angels waited on him.</verse>
      <verse name="14">Now after John was arrested, Jesus came to Galilee, proclaiming the good news of God,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Luke">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Since many have undertaken to set down an orderly account of the events that have been fulfilled among us,</verse>
      <verse name="2">just as they were handed on to us by those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses and servants of the word,</verse>
      <verse name="3">I too decided, after investigating everything carefully from the very first, to write an orderly account for you, most excellent Theophilus,</verse>
      <verse name="4">so that you may know the truth concerning the things about which you have been instructed.</verse>
      <verse name="5">In the days of King Herod of Judea, there was a priest named Zechariah, who belonged to the priestly order of Abijah. His wife was a descendant of Aaron, and her name was Elizabeth.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Both of them were righteous before God, living blamelessly according to all the commandments and regulations of the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="7">But they had no children, because Elizabeth was barren, and both were getting on in years.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Once when he was serving as priest before God and his section was on duty,</verse>
      <verse name="9">he was chosen by lot, according to the custom of the priesthood, to enter the sanctuary of the Lord and offer incense.</verse>
      <verse name="10">Now at the time of the incense offering, the whole assembly of the people was praying outside.</verse>
      <verse name="11">Then there appeared to him an angel of the Lord, standing at the right side of the altar of incense.</verse>
      <verse name="12">When Zechariah saw him, he was terrified; and fear overwhelmed him.</verse>
      <verse name="13">But the angel said to him, "Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has been heard. Your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son, and you will name him John.</verse>
      <verse name="14">You will have joy and gladness, and many will rejoice at his birth,</verse>
      <verse name="15">for he will be great in the sight of the Lord. He must never drink wine or strong drink; even before his birth he will be filled with the Holy Spirit.</verse>
      <verse name="16">He will turn many of the people of Israel to the Lord their God.</verse>
      <verse name="17">With the spirit and power of Elijah he will go before him, to turn the hearts of parents to their children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the righteous, to make ready a people prepared for the Lord."</verse>
      <verse name="18">Zechariah said to the angel, "How will I know that this is so? For I am an old man, and my wife is getting on in years."</verse>
      <verse name="19">The angel replied, "I am Gabriel. I stand in the presence of God, and I have been sent to speak to you and to bring you this good news.</verse>
      <verse name="20">But now, because you did not believe my words, which will be fulfilled in their time, you will become mute, unable to speak, until the day these things occur."</verse>
      <verse name="21">Meanwhile the people were waiting for Zechariah, and wondered at his delay in the sanctuary.</verse>
      <verse name="22">When he did come out, he could not speak to them, and they realized that he had seen a vision in the sanctuary. He kept motioning to them and remained unable to speak.</verse>
      <verse name="23">When his time of service was ended, he went to his home.</verse>
      <verse name="24">After those days his wife Elizabeth conceived, and for five months she remained in seclusion. She said,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="John">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.</verse>
      <verse name="2">He was in the beginning with God.</verse>
      <verse name="3">All things came into being through him, and without him not one thing came into being. What has come into being</verse>
      <verse name="4">in him was life, and the life was the light of all people.</verse>
      <verse name="5">The light shines in the darkness, and the darkness did not overcome it.</verse>
      <verse name="6">There was a man sent from God, whose name was John.</verse>
      <verse name="7">He came as a witness to testify to the light, so that all might believe through him.</verse>
      <verse name="8">He himself was not the light, but he came to testify to the light.</verse>
      <verse name="9">The true light, which enlightens everyone, was coming into the world.</verse>
      <verse name="10">He was in the world, and the world came into being through him; yet the world did not know him.</verse>
      <verse name="11">He came to what was his own, and his own people did not accept him.</verse>
      <verse name="12">But to all who received him, who believed in his name, he gave power to become children of God,</verse>
      <verse name="13">who were born, not of blood or of the will of the flesh or of the will of man, but of God.</verse>
      <verse name="14">And the Word became flesh and lived among us, and we have seen his glory, the glory as of a father's only son, full of grace and truth.</verse>
      <verse name="15">(John testified to him and cried out, "This was he of whom I said, 'He who comes after me ranks ahead of me because he was before me.'")</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Acts of the Apostles">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">In the first book, Theophilus, I wrote about all that Jesus did and taught from the beginning</verse>
      <verse name="2">until the day when he was taken up to heaven, after giving instructions through the Holy Spirit to the apostles whom he had chosen.</verse>
      <verse name="3">After his suffering he presented himself alive to them by many convincing proofs, appearing to them during forty days and speaking about the kingdom of God.</verse>
      <verse name="4">While staying with them, he ordered them not to leave Jerusalem, but to wait there for the promise of the Father. "This," he said, "is what you have heard from me;</verse>
      <verse name="5">for John baptized with water, but you will be baptized with the Holy Spirit not many days from now."</verse>
      <verse name="6">So when they had come together, they asked him, "Lord, is this the time when you will restore the kingdom to Israel?"</verse>
      <verse name="7">He replied, "It is not for you to know the times or periods that the Father has set by his own authority.</verse>
      <verse name="8">But you will receive power when the Holy Spirit has come upon you; and you will be my witnesses in Jerusalem, in all Judea and Samaria, and to the ends of the earth."</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Romans">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, set apart for the gospel of God,</verse>
      <verse name="2">which he promised beforehand through his prophets in the holy scriptures,</verse>
      <verse name="3">the gospel concerning his Son, who was descended from David according to the flesh</verse>
      <verse name="4">and was declared to be Son of God with power according to the spirit of holiness by resurrection from the dead, Jesus Christ our Lord,</verse>
      <verse name="5">through whom we have received grace and apostleship to bring about the obedience of faith among all the Gentiles for the sake of his name,</verse>
      <verse name="6">including yourselves who are called to belong to Jesus Christ,</verse>
      <verse name="7">To all God's beloved in Rome, who are called to be saints: Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="8">First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for all of you, because your faith is proclaimed throughout the world.</verse>
      <verse name="9">For God, whom I serve with my spirit by announcing the gospel of his Son, is my witness that without ceasing I remember you always in my prayers,</verse>
      <verse name="10">asking that by God's will I may somehow at last succeed in coming to you.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Corinthians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, called to be an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, and our brother Sosthenes,</verse>
      <verse name="2">To the church of God that is in Corinth, to those who are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, together with all those who in every place call on the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, both their Lord and ours:</verse>
      <verse name="3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="4">I give thanks to my God always for you because of the grace of God that has been given you in Christ Jesus,</verse>
      <verse name="5">for in every way you have been enriched in him, in speech and knowledge of every kind-</verse>
      <verse name="6">just as the testimony of Christ has been strengthened among you-</verse>
      <verse name="7">so that you are not lacking in any spiritual gift as you wait for the revealing of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="8">He will also strengthen you to the end, so that you may be blameless on the day of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="9">God is faithful; by him you were called into the fellowship of his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="10">Now I appeal to you, brothers and sisters, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that all of you be in agreement and that there be no divisions among you, but that you be united in the same mind and the same purpose.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Corinthians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, and Timothy our brother, To the church of God that is in Corinth, including all the saints throughout Achaia:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of mercies and the God of all consolation,</verse>
      <verse name="4">who consoles us in all our affliction, so that we may be able to console those who are in any affliction with the consolation with which we ourselves are consoled by God.</verse>
      <verse name="5">For just as the sufferings of Christ are abundant for us, so also our consolation is abundant through Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="6">If we are being afflicted, it is for your consolation and salvation; if we are being consoled, it is for your consolation, which you experience when you patiently endure the same sufferings that we are also suffering.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Our hope for you is unshaken; for we know that as you share in our sufferings, so also you share in our consolation.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Galatians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul an apostle- sent neither by human commission nor from human authorities, but through Jesus Christ and God the Father, who raised him from the dead-</verse>
      <verse name="2">and all the members of God's family who are with me, To the churches of Galatia:</verse>
      <verse name="3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
      <verse name="4">who gave himself for our sins to set us free from the present evil age, according to the will of our God and Father,</verse>
      <verse name="5">to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.</verse>
      <verse name="6">I am astonished that you are so quickly deserting the one who called you in the grace of Christ and are turning to a different gospel-</verse>
      <verse name="7">not that there is another gospel, but there are some who are confusing you and want to pervert the gospel of Christ.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Ephesians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, To the saints who are in Ephesus and are faithful in Christ Jesus:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us in Christ with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places,</verse>
      <verse name="4">just as he chose us in Christ before the foundation of the world to be holy and blameless before him in love.</verse>
      <verse name="5">He destined us for adoption as his children through Jesus Christ, according to the good pleasure of his will,</verse>
      <verse name="6">to the praise of his glorious grace that he freely bestowed on us in the Beloved.</verse>
      <verse name="7">In him we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Philippians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul and Timothy, servants of Christ Jesus, To all the saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, with the bishops and deacons:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="3">I thank my God every time I remember you,</verse>
      <verse name="4">constantly praying with joy in every one of my prayers for all of you,</verse>
      <verse name="5">because of your sharing in the gospel from the first day until now.</verse>
      <verse name="6">I am confident of this, that the one who began a good work among you will bring it to completion by the day of Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="7">It is right for me to think this way about all of you, because you hold me in your heart, for all of you share in God's grace with me, both in my imprisonment and in the defense and confirmation of the gospel.</verse>
      <verse name="8">For God is my witness, how I long for all of you with the compassion of Christ Jesus.</verse>
      <verse name="9">And this is my prayer, that your love may overflow more and more with knowledge and full insight</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Colossians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, and Timothy our brother,</verse>
      <verse name="2">To the saints and faithful brothers and sisters in Christ in Colossae: Grace to you and peace from God our Father.</verse>
      <verse name="3">In our prayers for you we always thank God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,</verse>
      <verse name="4">for we have heard of your faith in Christ Jesus and of the love that you have for all the saints,</verse>
      <verse name="5">because of the hope laid up for you in heaven. You have heard of this hope before in the word of the truth, the gospel</verse>
      <verse name="6">that has come to you. Just as it is bearing fruit and growing in the whole world, so it has been bearing fruit among yourselves from the day you heard it and truly comprehended the grace of God.</verse>
      <verse name="7">This you learned from Epaphras, our beloved fellow servant. He is a faithful minister of Christ on your behalf,</verse>
      <verse name="8">and he has made known to us your love in the Spirit.</verse>
      <verse name="9">For this reason, since the day we heard it, we have not ceased praying for you and asking that you may be filled with the knowledge of God's will in all spiritual wisdom and understanding,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Thessalonians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, To the church of the Thessalonians in God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ: Grace to you and peace.</verse>
      <verse name="2">We always give thanks to God for all of you and mention you in our prayers, constantly</verse>
      <verse name="3">remembering before our God and Father your work of faith and labor of love and steadfastness of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Thessalonians">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy, To the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:</verse>
      <verse name="2">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="3">We must always give thanks to God for you, brothers and sisters, as is right, because your faith is growing abundantly, and the love of everyone of you for one another is increasing.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Therefore we ourselves boast of you among the churches of God for your steadfastness and faith during all your persecutions and the afflictions that you are enduring.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Timothy">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the command of God our Savior and of Christ Jesus our hope,</verse>
      <verse name="2">To Timothy, my loyal child in the faith: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="3">I urge you, as I did when I was on my way to Macedonia, to remain in Ephesus so that you may instruct certain people not to teach any different doctrine,</verse>
      <verse name="4">and not to occupy themselves with myths and endless genealogies that promote speculations rather than the divine training that is known by faith.</verse>
      <verse name="5">But the aim of such instruction is love that comes from a pure heart, a good conscience, and sincere faith.</verse>
      <verse name="6">Some people have deviated from these and turned to meaningless talk,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Timothy">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, for the sake of the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus,</verse>
      <verse name="2">To Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="3">I am grateful to God- whom I worship with a clear conscience, as my ancestors did -when I remember you constantly in my prayers night and day.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Recalling your tears, I long to see you so that I may be filled with joy.</verse>
      <verse name="5">I am reminded of your sincere faith, a faith that lived first in your grandmother Lois and your mother Eunice and now, I am sure, lives in you.</verse>
      <verse name="6">For this reason I remind you to rekindle the gift of God that is within you through the laying on of my hands;</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Titus">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ, for the sake of the faith of God's elect and the knowledge of the truth that is in accordance with godliness,</verse>
      <verse name="2">in the hope of eternal life that God, who never lies, promised before the ages began-</verse>
      <verse name="3">in due time he revealed his word through the proclamation with which I have been entrusted by the command of God our Savior,</verse>
      <verse name="4">To Titus, my loyal child in the faith we share: Grace and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior.</verse>
      <verse name="5">I left you behind in Crete for this reason, so that you should put in order what remained to be done, and should appoint elders in every town, as I directed you:</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Philemon">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy our brother, To Philemon our dear friend and co-worker,</verse>
      <verse name="2">to Apphia our sister, to Archippus our fellow soldier, and to the church in your house:</verse>
      <verse name="3">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="4">When I remember you in my prayers, I always thank my God</verse>
      <verse name="5">because I hear of your love for all the saints and your faith toward the Lord Jesus.</verse>
      <verse name="6">I pray that the sharing of your faith may become effective when you perceive all the good that we may do for Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="7">I have indeed received much joy and encouragement from your love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed through you, my brother.</verse>
      <verse name="8">For this reason, though I am bold enough in Christ to command you to do your duty,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Hebrews">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Long ago God spoke to our ancestors in many and various ways by the prophets,</verse>
      <verse name="2">but in these last days he has spoken to us by a Son, whom he appointed heir of all things, through whom he also created the worlds.</verse>
      <verse name="3">He is the reflection of God's glory and the exact imprint of God's very being, and he sustains all things by his powerful word. When he had made purification for sins, he sat down at the right hand of the Majesty on high,</verse>
      <verse name="4">having become as much superior to angels as the name he has inherited is more excellent than theirs.</verse>
      <verse name="5">For to which of the angels did God ever say, "You are my Son; today I have begotten you"? Or again, "I will be his Father, and he will be my Son"?</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="James">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">James, a servant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, To the twelve tribes in the Dispersion: Greetings.</verse>
      <verse name="2">My brothers and sisters, whenever you face trials of any kind, consider it nothing but joy,</verse>
      <verse name="3">because you know that the testing of your faith produces endurance;</verse>
      <verse name="4">and let endurance have its full effect, so that you may be mature and complete, lacking in nothing.</verse>
      <verse name="5">If any of you is lacking in wisdom, ask God, who gives to all generously and ungrudgingly, and it will be given you.</verse>
      <verse name="6">But ask in faith, never doubting, for the one who doubts is like a wave of the sea, driven and tossed by the wind;</verse>
      <verse name="7">for the doubter, being double-minded and unstable in every way, must not expect to receive anything from the Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="9">Let the believer who is lowly boast in being raised up,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 Peter">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, To the exiles of the Dispersion in Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia,</verse>
      <verse name="2">who have been chosen and destined by God the Father and sanctified by the Spirit to be obedient to Jesus Christ and to be sprinkled with his blood: May grace and peace be yours in abundance.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ! By his great mercy he has given us a new birth into a living hope through the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead,</verse>
      <verse name="4">and into an inheritance that is imperishable, undefiled, and unfading, kept in heaven for you,</verse>
      <verse name="5">who are being protected by the power of God through faith for a salvation ready to be revealed in the last time.</verse>
      <verse name="6">In this you rejoice, even if now for a little while you have had to suffer various trials,</verse>
      <verse name="7">so that the genuineness of your faith- being more precious than gold that, though perishable, is tested by fire -may be found to result in praise and glory and honor when Jesus Christ is revealed.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Although you have not seen him, you love him; and even though you do not see him now, you believe in him and rejoice with an indescribable and glorious joy,</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 Peter">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Simeon Peter, a servant and apostle of Jesus Christ, To those who have received a faith as precious as ours through the righteousness of our God and Savior Jesus Christ:</verse>
      <verse name="2">May grace and peace be yours in abundance in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord.</verse>
      <verse name="3">His divine power has given us everything needed for life and godliness, through the knowledge of him who called us by his own glory and goodness.</verse>
      <verse name="4">Thus he has given us, through these things, his precious and very great promises, so that through them you may escape from the corruption that is in the world because of lust, and may become participants of the divine nature.</verse>
      <verse name="5">For this very reason, you must make every effort to support your faith with goodness, and goodness with knowledge,</verse>
      <verse name="6">and knowledge with self-control, and self-control with endurance, and endurance with godliness,</verse>
      <verse name="7">and godliness with mutual affection, and mutual affection with love.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="1 John">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">We declare to you what was from the beginning, what we have heard, what we have seen with our eyes, what we have looked at and touched with our hands, concerning the word of life-</verse>
      <verse name="2">this life was revealed, and we have seen it and testify to it, and declare to you the eternal life that was with the Father and was revealed to us-</verse>
      <verse name="3">we declare to you what we have seen and heard so that you also may have fellowship with us; and truly our fellowship is with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="2 John">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The elder to the elect lady and her children, whom I love in the truth, and not only I but also all who know the truth,</verse>
      <verse name="2">because of the truth that abides in us and will be with us forever:</verse>
      <verse name="3">Grace, mercy, and peace will be with us from God the Father and from Jesus Christ, the Father's Son, in truth and love.</verse>
      <verse name="4">I was overjoyed to find some of your children walking in the truth, just as we have been commanded by the Father.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="3 John">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The elder to the beloved Gaius, whom I love in truth.</verse>
      <verse name="2">Beloved, I pray that all may go well with you and that you may be in good health, just as it is well with your soul.</verse>
      <verse name="3">I was overjoyed when some of the friends arrived and testified to your faithfulness to the truth, namely how you walk in the truth.</verse>
      <verse name="4">I have no greater joy than this, to hear that my children are walking in the truth.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Beloved, you do faithfully whatever you do for the friends, even though they are strangers to you;</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Jude">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">Jude, a servant of Jesus Christ and brother of James, To those who are called, who are beloved in God the Father and kept safe for Jesus Christ:</verse>
      <verse name="2">May mercy, peace, and love be yours in abundance.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Beloved, while eagerly preparing to write to you about the salvation we share, I find it necessary to write and appeal to you to contend for the faith that was once for all entrusted to the saints.</verse>
      <verse name="4">For certain intruders have stolen in among you, people who long ago were designated for this condemnation as ungodly, who pervert the grace of our God into licentiousness and deny our only Master and Lord, Jesus Christ.</verse>
      <verse name="5">Now I desire to remind you, though you are fully informed, that the Lord, who once for all saved a people out of the land of Egypt, afterward destroyed those who did not believe.</verse>
      <verse name="6">And the angels who did not keep their own position, but left their proper dwelling, he has kept in eternal chains in deepest darkness for the judgment of the great Day.</verse>
      <verse name="7">Likewise, Sodom and Gomorrah and the surrounding cities, which, in the same manner as they, indulged in sexual immorality and pursued unnatural lust, serve as an example by undergoing a punishment of eternal fire.</verse>
      <verse name="8">Yet in the same way these dreamers also defile the flesh, reject authority, and slander the glorious ones.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
  <book name="Revelation">
    <chapter name="1">
      <verse name="1">The revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave him to show his servants what must soon take place; he made it known by sending his angel to his servant John,</verse>
      <verse name="2">who testified to the word of God and to the testimony of Jesus Christ, even to all that he saw.</verse>
      <verse name="3">Blessed is the one who reads aloud the words of the prophecy, and blessed are those who hear and who keep what is written in it; for the time is near.</verse>
      <verse name="4">John to the seven churches that are in Asia: Grace to you and peace from him who is and who was and who is to come, and from the seven spirits who are before his throne,</verse>
      <verse name="5">and from Jesus Christ, the faithful witness, the firstborn of the dead, and the ruler of the kings of the earth. To him who loves us and freed us from our sins by his blood,</verse>
      <verse name="6">and made us to be a kingdom, priests serving his God and Father, to him be glory and dominion forever and ever. Amen.</verse>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</root>